{
  "reference_number": "8152",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The current government is a coalition of parties that have disparate goals and should not be locking in legislation that will effect New\n\n Zealanders for decades to come, as they do not have a mandate for this. Setting a goal and a non political body of scientists and\n engineers that can then take into account information as it evolves would be prudent."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Must include overseas offsets particularly in CO2."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "New Zealand cannot act alone and the onus should be on enabling real progress in reducing overseas emissions not disabling the\n\n NZ economy. Export of NZ LNG/gas based methanol would achieve a remarkable impact."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Over the last 3 decades various claims have been made around climate change trajectory risks and benefits, understanding of these\n will change with time. The climate is dynamic and decision making should be also."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Technology and understanding can change in 5 years a 3 year target and 5 of them is more appropriate."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I believe that all the budgets should be subject to review by government and the commission based on new information and the\nlatest thinking not just the third budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However there should also be a focus on the global opportunities to reduce emissions elsewhere despite generation of emissions\n\nlocals and the offsetting of this."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ energy needs costs and energy security (working with treasury and industry), the needs of overseas developing nations that\nrequire energy (working with the UN)"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There needs to be an additional function of interacting with the global forums on climate change as the single voice of the NZ\n\ngovernment. This is a global problem not a local one."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "international business competitiveness needs to be a skill represented as does climate mitigation in a global sense (may come\n\nthrough the climate person) and global emission trading. The members should be a-political and required to act on the basis of facts\nand informed thinking not ideology, and also recruited without racial bias."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "climate has been changing for the worlds history and particularly since the last ice age, humans need to adapt to a changing climate\n\nor they go the way of the Babylonians, Romans and Mayans all of whom suffered catastrophic change due to changes in climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The functions look at climate change as a negative \"risk\" only the remit needs to look also at benefits that will arise from climate\nchanges and how we can capture these."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "information is valuable in a market economy it ensures correct decisions are taken."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The climate has been changing since the last ice age, and at times much more rapidly than at present. The commission needs to\ntake a balanced and informed view of the issues involved as the financial and living standard implications of changes in our climate.\n\nEnergy will be an important element in allowing us to cope with climate change, and the loss of the benefits of farming and energy\nproduction to New Zealanders has to be carefully weighed against the greenhouse gas emission effects, and how these fit into the\n\nglobal emissions pool. Mans effect on the climate is a global issue and should be resolved primarily at global forums."
    }
  ]
}
